Learning-SICP学习小组
倾情制作
计算机程序的构造和解释
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
翻译&&时间轴
刘殊君（rtmagic）
校对
邓雄飞
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
Generic Operators
通用运算符
PROFESSOR: So far in this course we've been talking
教授：到目前为止 我们已经进行了很多
a lot about data abstraction.
关于数据抽象的讨论
And remember the idea is that we build systems
关键理念就是在构造系统的时候
that have these horizontal barriers in them, these abstraction barriers
在其中加入水平的抽象屏障 这些抽象屏障
that separate use, the way you might use some data object,
把你使用一个数据对象的方式
from the way you might represent it.
和表示它的方式区分开来
Or another way to think of that is up here you have the boss
或者可以这样理解它 在上层有一个老板
who's going to be using some sort of data object.
想要调用某种数据对象
And down here is George who's implemented it.
而在下层 George负责它的具体实现
Now this notion of separating use from representation
这种把使用与表示分离的想法
so you can think about these two problems separately
可以让你分开考虑这两个问题
is a very,very powerful programming methodology, data abstraction.
这是一种非常强大的编程的方法论 -- 数据抽象
On the other hand, it's not really sufficient
但另一方面 数据抽象在那些真正复杂的系统上
for really complex systems.
并不是很有效
And the problem with this is George.
这个问题就出在George这里
Or actually, the problem is that
或者说 实际上 问题就在于
there are a lot of Georges.
现在有太多的George
Let's be concrete.
具体地说
Let's suppose there is George,and there's also Martha.
假设现在有George和Martha两个人
OK, now George and Martha are both working on this system,
他们都是这个系统的开发人员
both designing representations,
都在设计数据的表示方法
and absolutely are incompatible.
而且他们完全合不来
They wouldn't cooperate on a representation
他们不会合作开发同一种表示方法
under any circumstances.
永远也不会
And the problem is you would like to have some system
现在的问题是 假设你想要这样一个系统
where both George and Martha are designing representations,
在这个系统中George和Martha都为它设计了数据表示方法
and, yet, if you're above this abstraction barrier
但是如果你在高于这个抽象屏障的层面思考
you don't want to have to worry about that,
你就不用去操心这些事情
whether something is done by George or by Martha.
不用操心 某个东西是到底是George做的还是Martha做的
And you don't want George and Martha to
同时你也不想让George和Martha
interfere with each other.
妨碍彼此的工作
Somehow in designing a system, you not only want these
你在设计系统的时候 不仅仅需要这些
horizontal barriers, but you also want some kind of
水平的抽象屏障 同时也想设置一道
some kind of vertical barrier to keep George and Martha separate.
垂直的屏障 -- 来把George和Martha分离开
Let me be a little bit more concrete.
我们来说得再具体一点
Imagine that you're thinking about personnel records
想象一个很大的公司的人事记录
for a large company with a lot of loosely linked divisions
这个公司里有很多部门没什么联系
that don't cooperate very well either.
并且部门之间合作得也不太好
And imagine even that this company is formed by merging a
甚至还可以想象这个大公司就是由
whole bunch of companies that already have their personnel
很多公司组成的 而且每个公司
record system set up.
都有自己的一套人事记录
And imagine that once these divisions are all linked in
想象一下突然有一天 这些部门
some kind of very sophisticated satellite
被一种神奇的卫星网络连接起来
network, and all these databases are put together.
它们各自的数据库都被放到了一起
And what you'd like to do
现在你想要
is from any place in the company,
在公司的任何地方
to be able to say things like,oh, what's the name in a
都能够知道 哦 某一条人事记录里的
personnel record?
“姓名”是什么
Or, what's the job description in a personnel record?
或者一条记录里的“工作”是什么
And not have to worry about the fact that each division
同时又不需要担心每一个部门
obviously is going to have completely separate
对于人事记录的格式
conventions for how you might implement these records.
有着完全不同的习惯
From this point you don't want to know about that.
从你的视角上你不想去了解这些东西
Well how could you possibly do that?
那么怎么才能做到这样呢？
One way, of course, is to send down an edict from somewhere
当然 一种方法是下发一个告示
that everybody has to change their format to some fixed
来通知所有人把他们的记录格式
compatible thing.
都改成某种标准的格式
That's what people often try, and of course it never works.
人们经常这样做 但都没有成功
Another thing that you might want to do is somehow arrange
另一个办法则是重新安排这些记录
it so you can have these vertical barriers.
让它们中间有这种垂直的抽象屏障
So that when you ask for the name of a personnel record,
当你查询一份人事档案里的姓名的时候
somehow, whatever format it happens to be, name will
不管它是什么格式 name这个过程都能设法
figure out how to do the right thing.
搞清楚怎么正确地完成这件事
We want name to be, so-called, a generic operator.
我们把name叫做一个 所谓的“通用运算符”
Generic operator means what it sort of precisely does depends
通用运算符意味着它会根据数据的种类
on the kind of data that it's looking at.
准确地做出对应的操作
More than that, you'd like to design the system so that the
更进一步讲 你想让这个系统在
next time a new division comes into the company
下次公司里多了一个新的人员划分的时候
they don't have to make any big changes in what they're already doing
人们连接系统的方法不会有很大的变化
to link into this system, and the rest of the company
并且公司里剩下的部门
doesn't have to make any big changes
要把它们的人员记录添加到这个系统
to admit their stuff to the system.
也不需要做什么大的修改
So that's the problem you should be thinking about.
那么这就是你应该考虑的问题
Like it's sort of just your work.
或者这就是你的工作
You want to be able to include new things by making minimal changes.
要让系统可以用最少的改动来拥抱变化
OK, well that's the problem that we'll be talking about today.
这就是我们今天要讨论的问题
And you should have this sort of distributed personnel record system in your mind.
你脑子里应该有这个分布式的人事档案系统
But actually the one I'll be talking about is a problem
但是实际上 我今天要讨论的是一个
that's a little bit more self-contained than that.
比那要更加自成体系的问题
that'll bring up the issues, I think, more clearly.
我觉得用它可以把事情说得更清楚一点
That's the problem of doing a system that does arithmetic on complex numbers.
我们要讨论的是 复数域上的算术系统
So let's take a look here.
我们来看看这个系统
Just as a little review,
来复习一下
there are things called complex numbers.
什么是“复数”
Complex number you can think of as a point in the plane, or z.
复数z可以看做复平面上的一点
And you can represent a point either by its real-part and its imaginary-part.
我们将复数表示为实数部分和虚数部分
So if this is z and its real-part is this much,
所以如果这个是复数z 它的实部是这么多
and its imaginary-part is that much,
它的虚部是那么多
and you write z equals x plus iy.
我们就可以记z=x+iy
Or another way to represent a complex number is by saying,
还有另一种方法来表示一个复数 比如说
what's the distance from the origin, and what's the angle?
这个点与原点的距离是多少 在原点的什么角度上
So that represents a complex number as its radius times an angle.
像这样 复数也可以表示为半径乘以一个角度
This one's called -- the original one's called rectangular form,
第一种表示法称为 直角坐标系表示
rectangular representation, real- and imaginary-part
或者说实部-虚部表示
or polar representation magnitude and angle--
而后一种是用模和辐角两部分的极坐标表示
and if you know the real- and imaginary-part,
并且如果你知道了一个复数的实部和虚部
you can figure out the magnitude and angle.
你就能计算出它的模和辐角
If you know x and y, you can get r by this formula.
如果知道了x和y 就能用这个式子算出r
Square root of sum of the squares, and you can get the
等于两个数平方和的平方根 然后就可以
angle as an arctangent.
用反三角函数算出辐角的值
Or conversely, if you knew r and A you could
或者反过来 如果你知道了r和A
figure out x and y.
你也能计算出x和y
x is r times the cosine of A, and y is r times the sine of A.
x=r·cos(A) y=r·sin(A)
All right, so there's these two. They're complex numbers.
这是表示复数的两种不同方法
You can think of them either in polar form or rectangular form.
分别是极坐标形式和直角坐标形式
What we would like to do
我们要设计的是
is make a system that does arithmetic on complex numbers.
一个复数域上的算术系统
In other words, what we'd like--
换句话讲 我们要
just like the rational number example--
就像之前课上有理数运算的例子一样
is to have some operations plus c,
是构造一个叫做+c的操作
which is going to take two complex numbers and add them, subtract them,
它将两个复数然后把它们相加、相减
and multiply them, and divide them.
相乘或者相除
OK, well there's little bit of mathematics behind it.
那么我们要用到一点点数学
What are the actual formulas for manipulating such things?
对它们进行操作的具体的算式是什么
And it's sort of not important where they come from,
它们是怎么得出来的 并不重要
but just as an implementer let's see--
我们只是用它们实现运算
if you want to add two complex numbers it's pretty easy to
如果想要把两个复数相加
it's pretty easy to get its real-part and its imaginary-part.
可以很容易地获取它们的实部和虚部
The real-part of the sum of two complex numbers
两个复数的和的实部
real-part of the z1 plus z2
z1+z2的实部
is the real-part of z1 plus the real-part of z2.
就是z1的实部加上z2的实部
And the imaginary-part of z1 plus z2
然后z1+z2的虚部也就是
is the imaginary part of z1 plus the imaginary part of z2.
z1的虚部加上z2的虚部
So it's pretty easy to add complex numbers.
所以复数相加是非常简单的事情
You just add the corresponding parts
你只要把各个部分分别加起来
and make a new complex number with those parts.
然后用结果构建一个新的复数
If you want to multiply them,
如果你想要让复数相乘
it's kind of nice to do it in polar form.
那么在极坐标下运算会方便很多
Because if you have two complex numbers,
因为对于两个复数
the magnitude of their product is here, the product of the magnitudes.
两复数积之模 就是它们各自的模的乘积
And the angle of the product is the sum of the angles.
它们的积的辐角 就是两个辐角的和
So that's sort of mathematics that allows you to do arithmetic on complex numbers.
这就是复数域上的运算所需的数学知识
Let's actually think about the implementation.
我们来想一想具体的实现
Well we do it just like rational numbers.
我们就像之前运算有理数那样做
We come down, we assume we have some constructors and selectors.
来到底层 假设有一些构造函数和选择函数
What would we like?
它们应该是什么样子呢
Well let's assume that we make a data object cloud,
假设我们制造了一些表示数据对象的“云彩”
which is a complex number that has some stuff in it,
也就是用某种形式表示的复数
and that we can get out from a complex number the real-part,
我们能从这个复数中得到它的实部
or the imaginary-part, or the magnitude, or the angle.
可以获得 虚部、模、或者辐角
We want some ways of making complex numbers--
然后我们需要一种方法来构造复数
not only selectors, but constructors.
不仅要有选择函数 还要有构造函数
So we'll assume we have a thing called make-rectangular.
那么假设我们有一个叫做make-rectangular的过程
What make-rectangular is going to do is take a real-part and
这个过程的功能是接受一个实部
an imaginary-part and construct a complex number with those parts.
和一个虚部 然后把这两个部分组合成一个复数
Similarly, we can have make-polar which will taking
同样我们也可以构造一个make-polar过程
a magnitude and an angle,
它接受一个模和一个辐角
and construct a complex number which has that magnitude and angle.
然后用这两个值 组成一个复数
So here's a system.
那么这个系统
We'll have two constructors and four selectors.
里面会有两个构造函数和四个选择函数
And now, just like before, in terms of that abstract data
现在 就像之前课程中那样 我们基于这个抽象的数据结构
we'll go ahead and implement our complex number operations.
继续实现复数的各种运算
And here you can see translated into Lisp code
而这些Lisp代码
just the arithmetic formulas I put down before.
是从我之前写的算术公式“翻译”而来的
If I want to add two complex numbers
如果我想把两个复数相加
I will make a complex number out of its real- and imaginary-parts.
我就要用一个实部和一个虚部构造一个复数
The real part of the complex number I'm going to make
这个新的复数的实部是
is the sum of the real-parts.
两个复数的实部的和
The imaginary part of the complex number I'm going to make
它的虚数部分是
is the sum of the imaginary-parts.
两个复数的虚部的和
I put those together, make a complex number.
我把它们放到一起 构造出一个复数
That's how I implement complex number addition.
这就是实现复数加法的方法
Subtraction is essentially the same.
减法实际上是一样的
All I do is subtract the parts rather than add them.
只需要把各个部分相加变成把它们相减
To multiply two complex numbers,
要把两个复数相乘
I use the other formula.
要用另外一个式子
I'll make a complex number out of a magnitude and angle.
我会用一个模和一个辐角来构造一个复数
The magnitude
z1*z2的模
is going to be the product of the magnitudesof the two complex numbers I'm multiplying.
就是z1的模乘以z2的模
And the angle is going to be the sum
而z1*z2的辐角则是
of the angles of the z1two complex numbers I'm multiplying.
z1的辐角加上z2的辐角
So there's multiplication.
那么这就是乘法的实现
And then division,
然后是除法
division is almost the same.
除法和乘法几乎是一样的
Here I divide the magnitudes and subtract the angles.
我只要把两个模相除 把辐角相减就可以了
Now I've implemented the operations.
现在我已经实现了各种运算
And what do we do?
然后我们做什么
We call on George.
我们把George叫来
We've done the use, let's worry about the representation.
我们完成了“使用”的部分 现在应该考虑“表示”了
We'll call on George and say to George,
我们叫来George然后对他说
go ahead and build us a complex number representation.
“为我们设计一个一套复数的表示方法”
Well that's fine...ahhh
很好
George can say, we'll implement a complex number
George可能会说 我们把一个复数
simply as a pair that has the real-part and the imaginary-part.
实现为 一个由实部和虚部组成的序对
So if I want to make a complex number with a certain real-part and an imaginary-part,
那么如果我想用某个实部和虚部来构造复数
I'll just use cons to form a pair, and that will--
我只需要把它们cons起来即可 这样可以--
that's George's representation of a complex number.
这就是George表示复数的方法
So if I want to get out the real-part of something, I just
那么如果我想获得它的实部 我只需要
extract the car, the first part.
提取出序对的car部分 -- 它的首部分
If I want to get the imaginary-part, I extract the cdr
如果我想要得到虚部 我就提取出它的cdr部分
How do I deal with the magnitude and angle?
那对于模和辐角 又该如何取得呢？
Well if I want to extract the magnitude of one of these things
如果我想取得某个复数的模
I get the square root of the sum of the square of the car plus the square of the cdr.
我需要计算该复数car与cdr的平方和的算术平方根
If I want to get the angle, I compute the arctangent of the cdr in the car.
如果我想得到辐角 我就计算它的cdr与car比值的反正切
This is a lisp procedure for computing arctangent.
这个Lisp过程用于计算反正切
And if somebody hands me a magnitude and an angle
要是有人给我一个模和辐角
and says, make me a complex number,well I compute the
并说：“给我构造一个复数”
well I compute the real-part and the imaginary-part, r * cosine of a and r * sine of a,
用它们计算出实部 r*cos(a) 和虚部 r*sin(a)
and stick them together into a pair.
连接成一个序对就行了
OK so we're done.
完成了
In fact, what I just did, conceptually,
实际上我做的事情 在概念上讲
is absolutely no different from the rational number
和我们之前提过的有理数的表示
representation that we looked at last time.
是完全没有区别的
It's the same sort of idea.
它们的思想相同
You implement the operators, you pick a representation.
实现具体过程 选择一种表示方法
Nothing different.
没有什么不同
Now let's worry about Martha.
现在我们来关心一下Martha
See, Martha has a different idea.
嗯 Martha的想法不太一样
She doesn't want to represent a complex number
她不想把复数表示成
as a pair of a real-part and an imaginary-part.
由实部和虚部组成的序对
What she would like to do is represent a complex number as
她比较喜欢把它们表示成
a pair of a magnitude and an angle.
由模和辐角组成的序对
So if instead of calling up George we ask Martha to design
那么如果我们没有让George而是让Martha
our representation, we get something like this.
来设计复数的表示方法 我们就会得到这样的东西
We get make-polar.
有一个make-polar过程
Sure, if I give you a magnitude and an angle we're
当然了 有了一个模和一个辐角之后
just going to form a pair that has magnitude and angle.
我们只要把它们组合成一个序对就行了
If you want to extract the magnitude, that's easy.
如果你想取得复数的模 那很简单
You just pull out the car or the pair.
你只需要取序对的car部分即可
If you want to extract the angle, sure, that's easy.
当然 想取得复数的辐角 那也很简单
You just pull out the cdr.
只需取cdr部分即可
If you want to look for real-parts and imaginary-parts,
但是如果你想要获得实部和虚部
well then you have to do some work.
那就得费点力气
If you want the real-part, you have to get r cosine a.
想得到实部 你就得计算r*cos(a)
In other words, r, the car of the pair, times the cosine of
换句话讲 用序对的car部分去乘以
the cdr of the pair.
cdr部分的余弦值
So this is r times the cosine of a,
然后你就算出了r*cos(a)
and that's the real-part.
这就是这个复数的实部
If you want to get the imaginary-part, it's r times the sine of a.
要是想算出它的虚部 用r乘以sin(a)就可以了
And if I hand you a real-part and an imaginary-part and say,
现在如果我给你一个实部和虚部 然后说
make me a complex number with that real-part and
用它们给我构造一个复数
imaginary-part, well I figure out what the magnitude and
那就要先算出
angle should be.
模和辐角是多少
The magnitude's the square root of the sum of the squares
模是实部和虚部的平方和的算术平方根
and the angle's the arctangent.
辐角是这个反正切
I put those together to make a pair.
我用这两个数构造一个序对
So there's Martha's idea.
以上就是Martha的想法
Well which is better?
那么哪种比较好呢？
Well if you're doing a lot of additions, probably George's is better
如果你需要做很多加法 那么George的比较好
is better, because you're doing a lot of real-parts and imaginary-parts.
因为你总是要用到复数的实部和虚部
If mostly you're going to be doing multiplications and divisions,
如果你大多数时间都是在做乘法
then maybe Martha's idea is better.
那可能Martha的办法就要好一些
Or maybe, and this is the real point, you can't decide.
又或者 -- 这就是问题所在了 -- 你决定不了
Or maybe you just have to let them both hang around, for personality reasons.
或者出于某些个人原因 你想让它们同时存在
Maybe you just really can't ever decide what you would like.
也可能你是真的无法决定你更喜欢哪种表示法
And again, what we would really like is a system that looks like this.
回到这个话题 我们真正想要的是这样一个系统
That somehow there's George over here, who has built
这里面 既有George 他实现了
rectangular complex numbers.
复数的直角坐标表示
And Martha, who has polar complex numbers.
又有Martha 她实现了复数的极坐标表示
And somehow we have operations
然后我们有各种运算
that can add, and subtract, and multiply, and divide
用来对复数进行加减乘除
and it shouldn't matter
那么这些运算
that there are two incompatible representations of complex
不应该被系统中同时存在的两种
numbers floating around this system.
互不兼容的复数表示方法影响
In other words, not only like an abstraction barrier here
或者说 我们不光有像这样的一个抽象屏障
that has things in it like a real-part,
它里面有real-part
and an imaginary-part, and magnitude,and angle.
还有 IMAG-PART、MAG 和 ANG 等几个过程
So not only is there an abstraction barrier
不光有一层抽象屏障
that hides the actual representation from us,
把实际的数据表示隐藏起来
but also there's some kind of vertical barrier here
还有一层垂直的屏障
that allows both of these representations to exist
容许不同的表示方法彼此共存
without interfering with each other.
而不互相干预
The idea is that the things in here--
我们的想法是把这些东西
real-part, imaginary-part,magnitude, and angle--
REAL-PART、IMAG-PART、MAG、ANG 这些过程
will be generic operators.
设计成通用运算符
If you ask for the real-part, it will worry about
如果你调用real-part过程 它就会判断
what representation it's looking at.
要在哪一种表示方法中寻找它
OK, well how can we do that?
那么我们怎么做到这一点呢
There's actually a really obvious idea,
实际上有一个很容易想到的办法
if you're used to thinking about complex numbers.
如果你习惯了思考复数的模式
If you're used to thinking about compound data.
如果你已经习惯了复合数据的思想
See, suppose you could just tell by looking at a complex number
假设你只要观察一个复数
whether it was constructed by George or Martha.
就能看出它是被George还是Martha构造出来的
In other words, so it's not that what's floating around
换句话说 在你眼前漂浮的这些东西
here are ordinary, just complex numbers, right?
不是普通的复数 对吗？
They're fancy, designer complex numbers.
它们是被某个设计者“构想”出来的
So you look at a complex numbers as it's not just a complex number
当考察一个复数 我们会发现它“不仅仅”是个复数
it's got a label on it that says,
它上面有一个标签
that one is by Martha.
写着这个是由Martha制造的
Or this is a complex number by George.
或者这个是由George制造的
Right? They're signed.
对吧？它们被签了名字
See, and then whenever we looked at a complex number we
在这之后 无论何时我们看见一个复数
could just read the label, and then we'd know how you expect
我们只要看它的标签  然后我们就能知道
to operate on that.
应该怎么对它进行运算
In other words, what we want is not just ordinary data objects.
或者说 我们想要的不只是普通的数据对象
We want to introduce the notion of what's called typed data.
我们引入一个概念：带类型的数据
Typed data means, again, there's some sort of cloud.
带类型的数据就意味着 这里有一朵“云彩”
And what it's got in it is an ordinary data object like
它里面有我们之前所说的那种
we've been thinking about.
普通的数据对象
Pulled out the contents, sort of the actual data.
这是它的内容 就是实际的数据
But also a thing called a type,
它里面还有一个叫做类型的东西
but it's signed by either George or Martha.
被George或者Martha签了名
So we're going to go from regular data to type data.
那么我们现在就要从无类型的数据进入带类型数据的领域
How do we build that?
我们怎么构造它
Well that's easy.
那很简单
We know how to build clouds.
我们知道怎么构造“云彩”
We can build them out of pairs.
我们用序对来组成它们
So here's a little representation that supports typed data.
那么我们就有了一种方法来表示带类型的数据
There's a thing called take a type and attach it to a piece of contents,
这种方法叫做 把类型附加到内容上
and we just use cons.
用cons就可以做到
And if we have a piece of typed data, we can look at the type
然后面对一个带类型的数据 我们就可以知道它的类型
which is the car.
也就是序对的car部分
We can look at the contents,which is the cdr.
我们也可以知道它的具体内容 就是它的cdr部分
Now along with that, the way we use our type data will test,
我们用这种方法使用带类型的数据
when we're given a piece of data, what type it is.
面对一段类型数据就能知道它是什么类型
So we have some type predicates with us.
那么我们现在有了几种判断类型的谓词
For example, to see whether a complex number is one of
举例来讲 想要知道一个复数
George's, whether it's rectangular, we just check to
是不是George构造的 是不是直角坐标表示的 我们只需要看
see if the type of that is the symbol rectangular,
它的“类型”是不是rectangular这个符号
right? The symbol rectangular.
对吧？检查 rectangular 符号
And to check whether a complex number is one of Martha's,
同理 想要知道一个复数是不是Martha构造的
we check to see whether the type is the symbol polar.
我们就看它的“类型”是不是polar这个符号
So that's a way to test what kind of number we're looking at.
那么这就是一种识别数字的类型的方法
Now let's think about how we can use that to build the system.
现在来想想 怎么用这种方法来构建系统
So let's suppose that George and Martha were off working separately,
我们假设George和Martha分别在做各自的工作
and each of them had designed their complex number representation packages.
每一个人都设计了他们的复数表示程序包
What do they have to do to become part of the system,
他们怎么让自己的东西成为系统的一部分
to exist compatibly?
和对方友好共存呢
Well it's really pretty easy.
那其实非常简单
Remember, George had this package.
回忆一下 George做了这个程序包
Here's George's original package, or half of it.
这就是George的程序包 或者说它的一部分
And underlined in red are the changes he has to make.
然后红色下划线标出的部分是他需要做的修改
So before, when George made a complex number out of an x and y
之前 当George用x和y构建了一个复数的时候
he just put them together to make a pair.
他只是把它们组合成一个序对
And the only difference is that now he signs them.
现在唯一不同的地方是 他给它们打了标签
He attaches the type, which is the symbol rectangular to that pair.
他把类型 -- 也就是 rectangular符号 -- 附加到这个序对上面
Everything else George does is the same, except that--
剩下的事情都和之前一样 除了一点
see, George and Martha both have procedures named real-part and imaginary-part.
就是George和Martha的程序都有叫做real-part和imaginary-part的过程
So to allow them both to exist in the same Lisp environment,
为了这些过程存在于在同一个Lisp环境中
George had changed the names of his procedures.
George就要修改他的过程名字
So we'll say, this is George's real-part procedure.
那么我们说 这是George的real-part过程
It's the real-part-rectangular procedure,
叫做real-part-rectangular过程
the imaginary-part-rectangular procedure.
还有 imag-part-rectangular过程
And then here's the rest of George's package.
那么这里是George的程序包剩下的部分
He'd had magnitude and angle, just renames them magnitude
他已经有了magnitude和angle过程 只要把它们改名
rectangular and angle rectangular.
叫magnitude-rectangular和angle-rectangular就好了
And Martha has to do basically the same thing.
Martha要做的事情基本相同
Martha previously, when she made a complex number out of a magnitude and angle,
在这之前 当她用模和辐角构造复数的时候
she just cons them.
她只是把这两个东西cons起来
Now she attaches the type polar,
现在她额外附加类型 polar
and she changes the name
然后修改过程的名字
so her real-part procedure won't conflict in name with George's.
来避免保证她的real-part过程和George的产生冲突
It's a real-part-polar,imaginary-part-polar,
分别改为real-part-polar和imaginary-part-polar
magnitude polar, and angle polar.
magnitude-polar和angle-polar这四个过程
Now we have the system.
现在我们的系统
Right there's George and Martha.
在它里面既有George又有Martha
And now we've got to get some kind of manager to look at these types.
然后现在我们需要一个经理来对类型进行判断
How are these things actually going to work now
那么在George和Martha给我们提供了类型数据之后
that George and Martha have supplied us with typed data?
这个系统现在怎么工作呢？
Well what we have are a bunch of generic selectors.
我们手里有的 是一堆通用选择函数
Generic selectors for complex numbers real-part,imaginary-part, magnitude, and angle.
用于复数的通用选择函数比如 real-part、imag-part、magnitude和angle等
Let's look at them more closely.
让我们更进一步观察它们
What does a real-part do?
real-part过程应该做什么
If I ask for the real part of a complex number,
如果我想得到一个复数的实部
well I look at it.
那么我先要观察它
I look at its type.
我观察它的类型
I say, is it rectangular?
考虑它是用直角坐标表示的吗
If so, I apply George's real part procedure
如果是的话 我就对这个复数的"内容"部分
to the contents of that complex number.
调用George的real-part过程
This is a number that has a type on it.
这是一个带有类型的数字
I strip off the type using contents and apply George's procedure.
我用contents过程剥掉类型 并且对它应用George的过程
Or is this a polar complex number?
那如果是一个用极坐标表示的复数呢？
If I want the real part,
如果我想要得到它的实部
I apply Martha's real-part procedure to the contents of that number.
我就把Martha的real-part过程应用在这个数的内容上
So that's how real part works.
这就是real-part工作的方式
And then similarly there's imaginary-part, which is almost the same.
还有类似的imag-part过程 几乎是一样的
Right? It looks at the number and if it's rectangular, uses
它先观察这个数字 它是直角坐标表示的
George's imaginary-part procedure.
就调用George的imaginary-part过程
If it's polar, uses Martha's.
是极坐标表示的 就用Martha的过程
And then there's a magnitude and an angle.
同理也可以构造出magnitude和angle两个过程
So there's a system.
我们的系统是这个样子
Has three parts.
它里面有三个部分
There's sort of George, and Martha, and the manager.
有George、Martha和一个经理
And that's how you get generic operators implemented.
这就是实现通用操作符的方法
Let's look at just a simple example, just to pin it down.
为了把它说清楚 我们举一个简单的实例
But exactly how this is going to work,
但是准确描述了它工作的方式
suppose you're going to be looking at the complex number who's real-part is one,
假设你现在 面对一个实部是1
and who's imaginary-part is two.
虚部是2的复数
So that would be one plus 2i.
也就是1+2i
What would happen is up here,
现在在这里
up here above where the operations have to happen,
在操作发生的上层
that number would be represented as a pair of 1 and 2 together with type data.
复数被表示成一个由1和2组成的序对加上类型信息
That would be the contents.
（1和2）是内容
And the whole data would be that thing with the symbol rectangular added onto that.
整个的数据就是在那之上加上一个rectangular符号
And that's the way that complex number would exist in the system.
这就是复数在这个系统里存在的形式
When you went to take the real-part,
你要调取real-part的时候
the manager will look at this and say, oh it's one of George's.
经理会检查这个数然后说 这是George构造的数字
He'll strip off the type
他会先把类型拿掉
and hand down to George the pair 1, 2.
然后把 (1,2) 这个序对传递给George
And that's the kind of data that George developed his system to use.
这是George的系统可以直接处理的数据
So it gets stripped down.
那么它被拆了出来
Later on, if you ask George to construct a complex number,
之后 如果你让George构造一个复数
George would construct some complex number as a pair,
George就会把它构造成序对
and before he passes it back up through the manager would
在数据被传递到上层之前
attach the type rectangular.
经理会再给它加上rectangular类型
So you see what happens.
看这个过程
There's no confusion in this system.
这个系统不会发生混乱
It doesn't matter in the least that the pair 1, 2
就算在Martha的世界里 序对(1 2)的含义完全不同
means something completely different in Martha's world.
也并没有什么影响
In Martha's world this pair means the complex number whose
在Martha的世界里这个序对代表了
magnitude is 1 and whose angle is 2.
一个模为1 辐角为2的复数
And there's no confusion,
但是这并不会造成混乱
because by the time any pair like this gets handed back through the manager to the
因为每当有一个这样的序对经由经理之手
main system it's going to have the type polar attached.
被交给主系统的时候 它都会被附加上polar的类型标志
Whereas this one would have the type rectangular attached.
而这个就会被贴上rectangular类型的标签
OK, let's take a break.
好 我们休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Gerald Jay Sussman
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
Generic Operators
通用运算符
We just looked at a strategy for implementing generic operators.
我们刚刚提出了一种实现通用运算符的策略
That strategy has a name: it's called dispatch on type.
这种策略有一个名字 叫做“基于类型的分派”
And the idea is that you break your system into a bunch of pieces.
它的想法就是你要把你的系统分成很多小块
There's George and Martha, who are making representations,
里面有George和Martha在设计表示方法
and then there's the manager.
还有一个经理
Looks at the types on the data
负责去看数据上的类型是什么
and then dispatches them to the right person.
然后分派给正确的人去处理
Well what criticisms can we make of that as a system organization?
这种组织系统的方法有什么缺点呢？
Well first of all there was this little, annoying problem
首先 有个小小的烦人的问题
that George and Martha had to change the names of their procedures
George和Martha需要修改他们的过程的名字
George originally had a real-part procedure,
George一开始写了一个real-part过程
and he had to go name it real-part rectangular
现在他必须把它的名字改成real-part-rectangular
so it wouldn't interfere with Martha's real-part procedure,
才能让它不与Martha的real-part过程相互冲突
which is now named real-part-polar,
而Martha的过程现在改叫real-part-polar
so it wouldn't interfere with the manager's real-part procedure, who's now named real-part.
这是为了不和经理的那个叫做real-part的过程发生冲突
That's kind of an annoying problem.
这个问题确实很恼人
But I'm not going to talk about that one now.
但是我现在暂时不讨论这个问题
We'll see later on
我们稍后将会看到
when we think about the structure of Lisp names and environments
在讨论到Lisp名称与环境的结构的时候
that there really are ways to package all those so-called name spaces separately so they
我们会有方法把这些所谓的命名空间分开来封装
don't interfere with each other.
然后它们就不会互相影响了
Not going to think about that problem now.
现在我们暂时不去考虑这个问题
The problem that I actually want to focus on is
我现在想关注的问题是
what happens when you bring somebody new into the system.
你把一个新人招纳进系统之中会发生什么
What has to happen?
会发生什么？
Well George and Martha don't care.
George和Martha并不关心
George is sitting there in his rectangular world,
George在他的直角坐标世界里
has his procedures and his types.
坐拥着他的过程和数据类型
Martha sits in her polar world.
而Martha待在她的极坐标世界中
She doesn't care.
不问世事
But let's look at the manager.
但是经理呢？
What's the manager have to do?
经理需要做什么？
The manager comes through and had these operations.
现在经理带着他的运算来了
There was a test for rectangular
有直角坐标的判断
and a test for polar.
和极坐标的判断过程
If Harry comes in with some new kind of complex number,
如果Harry带着某种新型的复数表示方法 进入这个系统
and Harry has a new type, Harry type complex number, the
同时带来了一个新的类型--Harry型复数
manager has to go in and change all those procedures.
经理就需要修改他所有的过程
So the inflexibility in the system,
所以这个系统的不灵活之处
the place where work has to happen to accommodate change, is in the manager.
也就是需要大量工作才能适应变化的地方 就在这个经理身上
That's pretty annoying.
那是非常恼人的事情
It's even more annoying
更恼人的是
It's even more annoying when you realize the manager's not doing anything
你意识到这个经理实际上什么也不做
The manager is just being a paper pusher.
这个经理只负责“传递公文”而已
Let's look again at these programs. What are they doing?
我们再来看看这些程序 它们在做什么
What does real-part do?
real-part过程在做什么
Real-part says, oh, is it the kind of complex number that
这个过程说 哦 这个复数是
George can handle?
George会处理的那一种吗
If so, send it off to George.
如果是的话 好 把它交给George处理
Is it the kind of complex number that Martha can handle?
它是Martha能操作的那一种吗
If so, send it off to Martha.
是的话 把它交给Martha处理
So it's really annoying that the bottleneck in this system,
这个系统真正恼人之处 也就是这个系统的瓶颈
the thing that's preventing flexibility and change,
它降低灵活性 阻碍变化
is completely in the bureaucracy.
完全是一种的官僚主义
It's not in anybody who's doing any of the work.
而不是任何做实事的人
Not an uncommon situation, unfortunately.
很可惜这种情况经常发生
See, what's really going on--
实际上发生的事情是
abstractly in the system, there's a table.
在系统中 有一张抽象的表格
So what's really happening is somewhere there's a table.
实际发生的事情是 有这样一张表格
There're types.
其中有各种类型
There's polar and rectangular.
有polar和rectangular
And Harry's may be over here.
可能Harry也在这里
And there are operators.
然后这里是各种运算符
There's an operator like real-part. Or imaginary-part.
各种运算符 比如real-part和imag-part
Or a magnitude and angle.
还有magnitude、angle这些运算符
And sitting in this table are the right procedures.
单元格中对应的是相应过程
So sitting here for the type polar and real-part is
那么填在这里 负责polar类型的real-part过程的是
Martha's procedure real-part-polar.
Martha的real-part-polar过程
And over here in the table is George's procedure real-part-rectangular.
然后在这里是George的real-part-rectangular过程
And over here would be, say, Martha's procedure magnitude-polar,
然后这里是Martha的magnitude-polar过程
and George's procedure magnitude-rectangular, right, and so on.
然后是George的magnitude-rectangular过程 等等等等
The rest of this table's filled in.
剩下的单元格也像这样填好
And that's really what's going on.
这就是实际上发生的事情
So in some sense, all the manager is doing
从某种意义上讲 经理做的事情就是
is acting as this table.
去扮演这张表格
Well how do we fix our system?
那我们怎么去修补这个系统呢
Well, how do you fix bureaucracies a lot of the time?
怎么去消灭这种官僚主义？
What you do is you get rid of the manager.
你要做的就是让这个经理走人
We just take the manager and replace him by a computer.
我们用一台计算机来代替他
We're going to automate him out of existence.
我们要让自动操作抹掉他存在的意义
Namely, instead of having the manager who basically consults this table,
也就是说 我们不用这个经理去查阅这个表格
we'll have our system use the table directly.
而是让我们的系统直接去查阅它
What do I mean by that?
这是什么意思呢？
Let's assume, again using data abstraction,
我们来假设 还是用数据抽象的观点
that we have some kind of data structure that's a table.
我们有这样一种表格数据结构
And we have ways of sticking things in and ways of getting things out.
而且我们还有把东西填进去和从中删除的方法
And to be explicit, let me assume that there's an operation called "put."
为了把话说清楚 我们假设现在有一个叫put的方法
And put is going to take, case two things I'll call "keys." key1 and key2.
本例中put方法接受两个参数 -- 我们称其为“关键字” -- key1和key2
And a value.
还有接受一个值
And that stores the value in the table under key1 and key2.
put过程把value存放在表格key1和key2对应的格子里
And then we'll assume there's a thing called "get,"
然后我们假设有另一个叫get的过程
such that if later on I say, get me what's in the table
它是这样的一个东西 如果我说把表格里
stored under key1 and key2,
存储在key1和key2对应的格子中的数据给我
it'll retrieve whatever value was stored there.
它会把存储在那里的东西返回给我
And let's not worry about how tables are implemented.
我们先不要担心这个表格怎么实现
That's yet another data abstraction, George's problem.
那又是另一个数据抽象了 是George需要考虑的问题
And maybe we'll see later--
也许稍后我们还会看到
talk about how you might actually build tables in Lisp.
我们还会讨论怎么用Lisp建立这个表格
Well given this organization,what did George and Martha have to do?
我们有了这个组织结构 George和Martha需要做什么呢？
Well when they build their system,
当他们构建自己的系统的时候
they each have the responsibility
都有责任在表格里
to set up their appropriate column in the table.
正确地添加上自己的那一列
So what George does, for example,
比如说 对于George
when he defines his procedures all he has to do
当他定义过程的时候 他需要做的就是
is go off and put into the table under the type-rectangular.
把它们放进表格中的rectangular类型的那一列下面
And the name of the operation is real-part,
然后操作的名字是real-part
his procedure real-part-rectangular.
放入他的real-part-rectangular过程
So notice what's going into this table.
注意有什么被放到了表格里
The two keys here are symbols, rectangular and real-part.
这里的两个key是这两个符号：rectangular和real-part
That's the quote.
这是引用
And what's going into the table is the actual
要被填到表里的东西
procedure that he wrote, real-part rectangular.
是他编写的real-part-rectangular过程
And then puts an imaginary part into the table,
然后把这个获取虚部的过程也放进表里
filed under the keys rectangular and imaginary-part,
分类到rectangular和imag-part两个关键字之下
and magnitude under the keys rectangular magnitude,
获取模值的过程放到rectangular和magnitude下面
angle under rectangular-angle.
获取辐角的过程放到rectangular和angle下面
Okay? So that's what George has to do to be part of this system.
George作为系统的一部分 就要做以上这些事情
Martha similarly sets up the column and the table under polar.
Martha用同样的方法填好表格中关于polar的这一列
Polar and real-part.
在polar和real-part对应的这一栏
Right? Is the procedure real-part-polar?
应该填的过程是real-part-polar是吧？
And imaginary-part, and magnitude, and angle.
然后分别是imag-part、magnitude和angle过程
So this is what Martha has to do to be part of the system.
Martha想要加入系统当中就要做这些事情
Everyone who makes a representation has the
每个设计了数据表示的人
responsibility for setting up a column in the table.
都必须在表格里设置自己的一列
And what does Harry do when Harry comes in with his
那么Harry带着他的绝妙的复数实现方法
brilliant idea for implementing complex numbers?
过来的时候 他需要做什么呢
Well he makes whatever procedure he wants and
他先把过程写好
builds a new column in this table.
然后在表格里再建立一列
OK, well what happened to the manager?
那么现在经理怎么样了呢
The manager has been automated out of existence and is
经理的存在被自动操作所取代
replaced by a procedure called operate.
被一个叫做operate的过程代替
And this is the key procedure in the whole system.
这是这个系统最关键的一个过程
Let's say define operate.
(define operate
Operate is going to take an operation that you want to do,
Operate过程接收你想要采取的运算
the name of an operation,
应该说是这个运算的名字
and an object that you would like to apply that operation to.
和被运算的对象
So for example, the real-part of some particular complex number, what does it do?
那么举例来说 对一个复数调用real-part operate过程会做什么呢
Well the first thing it does, it looks in the table.
它要做的第一件事就是去查表
Goes into the table
它查询这个表格
and tries to find a procedure that's stored in the table.
试图去找到存储在表格里的一个过程
So it gets from the table,
所以它要对表格调用get过程
using as keys the type of the object and the operator,
用对象的类型和运算的名称作为关键字进行检索
but looks on the table and sees
这样就可以知道在表格中
what's stored under the type of the object and the operator
与数据的类型和要进行的运算相对应的是什么了
sees if anything's stored.
对应的这一格里填了什么东西
Let's assume that get is implemented.
我们假设get过程已经被实现好了
So if nothing is stored there,
所以如果在那一格什么也没有
it'll return a nil, return the empty list.
它就会返回一个空表
So it says, if there's actually something stored there,
如果那里确实有什么东西
if the procedure here is not no,
如果存储有这样的一个过程
then it'll take the procedure that it found in the table
那么就会把在表格里找到的这个过程
procedure that it found in the table and apply it to the contents of the object.
应用到对象的具体内容上去
And otherwise if there was nothing stored there,
如果那里没有东西的话
it'll-- well we can decide.
它就会 -- 我们可以决定
In this case let's have it put out an error message saying, undefined operator.
本例中 我们让它输出一个错误消息：“未定义的运算符”
No operator for this type.
没有支持这种类型的运算符
Or some appropriate error message.
或者其它合适的错误信息
OK?
对吧？
And that replaces the manager.
这个东西替代了经理
How do we really use it?
我们怎么去使用它呢
Well what we say is we'll go off and define our generic selectors using operate.
我们的想法是用operate过程来定义通用选择函数
We'll say that the real-part of an object is found by
我们可以说一个对象的real-part
operating on the object with the name of the operation being real-part.
是这个对象被operate应用了叫做real-part的运算后得到的结果
And then similarly, imaginary-part is operate using the name imaginary-part
那么类似地 imag-part是operate对obj应用imag-part运算
and magnitude and angle.
magnitude和angle同理
That's our implementation.
这就是我们的实现方法
That plus the type plus the operate procedure.
由它们加上类型再加上operate过程组成
And the table effectively replaces what the  manager used to do.
这个表格现在就有效地完成了之前经理的工作
Let's just go through that slowly to show you what's going on.
我们来梳理一下在这个过程中发生的事情
Suppose I have one of Martha's complex numbers.
假设我有一个由Martha构造的复数
It's got magnitude 1 and angle 2.
它的模值是1 辐角是2
And it's one of Martha's.
它是由Martha构造的
So it's labeled here, polar.
所以它被贴上了polar的标签
Let's call that z.
我们叫它z
Suppose that's z.
假设这就是z
And suppose with this implementation someone comes up
然后假设在这种实现方法下
asks for the real-part of z.
有人想要取z的实部
Well real-part now is defined in terms of operate.
由于real-part现在是用operate来定义的
So that's equivalent to saying
这就等同于说
operate with the name of the operator being real-part, the symbol real-part on z.
调用 (operate 'real-part z)
And now operate comes.
然后operate过程
It's going to look in the table,
就会去查询表格
and it's going to try and find something stored under--
然后试图去寻找在表格里存放的
the operation is going to apply by looking in the table under the type of the object.
查询表格中与对象的类型相对应的一列
And the type of z is polar.
那么z的类型是polar
So it's going to look and say, can I get using polar?
所以它就要说 我用polar作为关键字查表
And the operation name, which was real-part.
然后运算的名称是real-part
It's going to look in there and apply that to the contents of z.
它查询对应的过程 然后应用到z的内容上去
What's that is if everything was set up correctly,
如果所有东西都安排妥当的话
this thing is the procedure that Martha put there.
如果它找到的过程就是Martha编写的过程
This is real-part-polar.
也就是real-part-polar
And this is z without its type.
然后这就是z去掉类型之后的东西
The thing that Martha originally designed those procedures to work on,
是Martha最初设计的数据表示
which is 1, 2.
也就是这里的(1 2)
And so operate sort of does uniformly
所以说在整个系统中 operate过程
what the manager used to do sort of all over the system.
和之前的经理做的事情没什么区别
It finds the right thing, looks in the table, strips off the type,
它通过查询表格找到正确的东西  然后剥离类型
and passes it down into the person who handles it.
然后把它传递给能够处理它的人
This is another, and, you can see, more flexible for most purposes,
你会发现 这是另一种 在大多数情况下
way of implementing generic operators.
更灵活地实现通用运算符的方法
And it's called data-directed programming.
我们把它叫做“数据导向编程”
And the idea of that is
其理念是
And the idea of that is in some sense the data objects themselves,
在某种意义上 这些数据对象本身
those little complex numbers that are floating around the system,
这些充斥在系统中的复数
are carrying with them the information about how you should operate on them.
它们自身就携带着 关于应该怎么去操作它们的信息
Let's break for questions.
有什么疑问吗？
Yes.
请说
AUDIENCE: What do you have stored in that data object?
学生：你在那个数据对象里存储的是什么呢
You have the data itself, you have its type,
这里面有这个数据本身 还有它的类型
the operations for that type?
还有该与该类型对应的运算
Or where are the operations that you found?
或者说那些运算是存储在哪里呢？
PROFESSOR: OK, let me--
教授：好 让我--
yeah, that's a good question.
恩 这是一个好问题
Because it raises other possibilities of how you might do it.
通过它暗示了实现我们目标的 其它可行方法
And of course there are a lot of possibilities.
当然可能的方法有很多
In this particular implementation,
在这个特定的实现当中
what's sitting in this data object, for example,
在这个数据对象里放着
is the data itself-- which in this case is a pair of 1 and 2--
就是数据本身 本例中是序对(1, 2)
and also a symbol.
和一个符号
This is the symbol, the word P-O-L-A-R,
就是这个符号 单词P-O-L-A-R
And that what's sitting in this data object.
这些就是这个数据对象里面的东西
OK, where are the operations themselves?
那么这些运算又是存放在哪里的呢？
The operations are sitting in the table.
那些运算在表格里
So in this table,
在这个表格里
the rows and columns of the table are labeled by symbols.
所有行和列的名字都是符号
So when I store something in this table,
所以当我往里面存什么东西的时候
the key might be the symbol polar and the symbol magnitude.
可以以符号polar或符号magnitude作为关键字
And I think by writing it this way I've been very confusing.
我这样写 可能让你们感到困惑了
Because what's really sitting here isn't--
因为在这里面放的并不是
when I wrote magnitude polar,
当我写下mag-polar的时候
what I mean is the procedure magnitude polar.
我指的是那个叫mag-polar的过程
And probably what I really should have written--
可能 我本来应该在这里写上
except it's too small for me to write
但是这里空间太小了
in this little space--
我写不下
is something like lambda of z,
应该写成lambda(z)
the thing that Martha wrote to implement.
然后调用Martha实现的过程
And then you can see from that,
你也可以从这里看出
there's another way that I alluded to
我已经暗示了另一种方法
of solving this name conflict problem
来解决名字冲突的问题
which is that George and Martha never have to name their procedures at all.
那就是George和Martha根本不用给他们的过程起名字
They can just stick the lambda, the lambda...
可以直接把由lambda定义的
the anonymous things generated by lambda directly into the table.
由lambda定义的匿名函数放进表格里
There's also another thing that your question raises,
你的问题还引出了另一种可能性
is the possibility that maybe
也就是
what I would like somehow is to store in this data object
可能我在这个数据对象里存储的
not the symbol P-O-L-A-R but
不是符号POLAR
maybe actually all the operations themselves.
也许是这些运算本身
And that's another way to organize the system,
这是组织系统的另一种方法
called message passing.
叫做“消息传递”
So there are a lot of ways you can do it.
它们都殊途同归
AUDIENCE: Therefore if Martha and George had used the same
学生：所以说如果Martha和George
procedure names, it would be OK because it wouldn't look
用了相同的过程名字也没什么问题
it wouldn't look into it
[听不清]
PROFESSOR: That's right.That's right.
教授：对 你说得很对
See, they wouldn't even have to name their procedures at all.
看 他们甚至根本不需要给他们的过程命名
What George and Martha could writ --,
George和Martha可以 --
what George could have written
George可以这么来做
instead of saying put in the table under rectangular- and real-part,
与其在rectangular和real-part对应的格子里放
the procedure real-part rectangular,
存放real-part-rectangular这个过程
George could have written put under rectangular real-part,
George可以在rectangular和real-part对应的格子里放
lambda of z, such and such, such and such,
放一个lambda(z) 然后什么什么
And the system would work completely the same.
整个系统会以完全相同的方式工作
AUDIENCE: My question is, Martha could put
学生：我的问题是 就算Martha在
could have put key1 key2 real-part,
Martha在key1和key2对应的格子里放了real-part过程
and George could have put key1 key2 real-part,
George也在key1和key2下放了一个real-part过程
and as long as they defined them differently
只要两个过程的定义不一样
they wouldn't have had any conflicts, right?
它们就不会发生任何冲突 对吗？
PROFESSOR: Yes, that would all be OK except for the fact
教授：对的 这完全没有问题
that if you imagine George and Martha typing at the same
除非你说的是George和Martha在同一个终端上工作
console with the same meanings for all their names,
并且他们两个人起的所有名字的含义全部相同
and it would get confused by real-part,
那么同样的real-part就会造成困扰
but there are ways to arrange that, too.
但是就算是这种情况也有办法解决
And in principle you're absolutely right.
从原则上讲你说的完全正确
If their names didn't conflict--
如果它们的名字不互相冲突的话
it's the objects that go in the table, not the names.
被填到表里的是对象本身 而不是它们的名字
OK, let's take a break.
好 我们休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
By: Prof. Harold Abelson && Gerald Jay Sussman
讲师： 哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
The Structure And Interpretation of Computer Programs
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
Generic Operators
通用运算符
RPOFESSOR: All right, well we just looked at data-directed programming
教授：好的 我们刚刚讲了一个数据导向编程的例子
as a way of implementing a system that does arithmetic on complex numbers.
我们将其用于实现一个复数域上的算术系统
So I had these operations in it called plus C and minus C,
我已经在里面实现了 +c -c 这些运算
and multiply, and divide,and maybe some others.
*c \c 还有其它的一些过程
And that sat on top of-- and this is the key point--
这些过程存在于上层 -- 这是关键之处
sat on top of two different representations.
它们存在于两种不同表示方式的上层
A rectangular package here, and a polar package.
这是一个直角坐标程序包 这里一个极坐标程序包
And maybe some more.
可能还有其它的东西
And we saw that the whole idea is that maybe some more are now very easy to add.
关键理念就是 “其它的东西”可以很容易地添加上去
But that doesn't really show the power of this methodology.
但是这并没有真正体现出这种方法学的威力
Shows you what's going on.
我们看看发生了什么
The power of the methodology only becomes apparent
这个方法的威力 只有当你
when you start embedding this in some more complex system.
当你把它嵌入于一些更复杂的系统中时才会显现
So let... What I'm going to do now
我现在要做的就是
is embed this in some more complex system.
把它嵌入一个更复杂的系统中
Let's assume that what we really have is a general kind of arithmetic system.
假设我们已经有了一个通用算术系统
So called generic arithmetic system.
所谓的“通用算术系统”
And at the top level here,
然后在系统的最顶层
somebody can say add twothings, or subtract two things,
用户可以命令它把两个东西相加 或者相减
or multiply two  things, or divide two things.
或者让两数相乘、相除
And underneath that there's an abstraction barrier.
然后在它们下面是一个抽象屏障
And underneath this barrier,
抽象屏障的下层
is, say, a complex arithmetic package.
是一个复数域算术程序包
And you can say, add two complex numbers.
然后你可以让它把两个复数相加
Or you might also have--remember we did a rational number package
或者你还可以把 有理数域算术程序包
you might have that sitting there.
给安装进来
And there might be a rational thing.
可以放进去有理数
And the rational number package,
然后有理数程序包里面
well, has the things we implemented. Plus rat, and times rat, and so on.
有我们实现的 +rat、*rat等等的这些过程
Or you might have ordinary Lisp numbers.
或者你还可以加上通常的Lisp算术系统
You might say add three and four.
你可以让它把3和4加起来
So we might have ordinary numbers,
那么我们在这个系统里加入通常的算术系统
in which case we have the Lisp supplied plus, and minus, and times, and slash.
其中有Lisp自带的 + - * /
OK, so we might imagine this complex number system
总而言之 我们可以想象这个复数系统
sitting in a more complicated generic operator structure at the next level up.
存在于一个更加复杂的通用运算系统里面
Well how can we make that?
我们怎么才能做到呢
We already have the idea, we're just going to do it again.
我们已经有了想法 只要再一次应用它就可以了
We've implemented a rational number package.
我们已经实现了一个有理数程序包
Let's look at how it has to be changed.
那么我们来看看应该怎么修改它
In fact, at this level it doesn't have to be changed at all.
实际上 在这个层面 它根本就不需要修改
This is exactly the code that we wrote last time.
这完全就是我们上次写的那些代码
To add two rational numbers,
要把两个有理数相加
remember there was this formula.
回忆一下 我们要用到这个公式
You make a rational number whose numerator--
构造一个有理数 它的分子是
is the numerator of the first times the denominator of the second
x的分子乘以y的分母
plus the denominator of the first times the numerator of the second.
加上 x的分母乘以y的分子
And who's denominator is the product of the denominators.
而结果的分母是 x的分母乘y的分母
And minus rat, and star rat, and slash rat.
然后是-rat、*rat、/rat这些过程
And this is exactly the rational number package that we made before.
这就是我们之前写的那个有理数程序包
We're ignoring the GCD problem,but let's not worry about that.
我们忽略最大公约数的问题 先不去考虑那个
How do we install... As implementers of this rational number package,
作为这个有理数包的实现人员
how do we install it in the generic arithmetic system?
怎么把它安装到我们的通用运算系统中呢？
Well that's easy.
那很简单
Go off... There's only one thing we have to do differently.
我们要做的事只有一件和之前不同
Whereas previously we said that to make a rational number
在之前我们说构造一个有理数
you built a pair of the numerator and denominator,
就是构造一个由分子分母组成的序对
here we'll not only build the pair, but we'll sign it.
现在我们不光构造这个序对 还要给它贴上标签
We'll attach the type rational.
给它加上rational类型
That's the only thing we have to do different,
这就是唯一的不同之处
make it a typed data object.
把它变成带类型的数据
And now we'll stick our operations in the table.
现在 我们要把运算放进表格里
We'll put under the symbol rational and the operation add
我们在rational符号和add运算对应的格子里
our procedure -- +rat.
放进我们的+rat过程
And, again, note this is a symbol.
再次强调 这是一个符号
Right?
看到了么？
Quote, and quote,
这是引用 这也是引用
but the actual thing we're putting in the table is the procedure.
但是实际上放进表里的是+rat过程本身
And for how to subtract,
然后怎么做减法
well you subtract rationals with minus rat.
我们用-rat过程做减法
And multiply, and divide.
然后是乘法和除法
And that is exactly and precisely what we have to do
这些步骤精准地描述了 我们该怎么做
to fit inside this generic arithmetic system.
来兼容这个通用算术系统
Well how does the whole thing work?
那么整个系统怎么工作呢
See, what we want to do is have some generic operators.
我们想实现的是通用运算符
Right? Have add and sub and mul and div be generic operators.
为了让add、sub、mul和div变成通用运算符
So we're going to define add and say, to add x and y,
所以我们要把add过程定义为 (ADD X Y)就是
that will be operate--
就是调用operate过程
we were going to call it operate-2.
我们把这个叫做operate-2
This is our operator procedure, but set up for two arguments
这是我们的操作过程 但是要接收两个参数
using add on x and y.
对它们应用add 把它们加起来
And so this is the analog to operate.
这是和operate类似的一个东西
Let's look at the code for a second.
我们再看看这个代码
It's almost like operate.
它和operate很相似
Right? To operate with some operator on an argument1 and an argument2
为了将运算符运用在两个参数arg1和arg2上
well the first thing we're going to do is check
首要任务是
and see if the two arguments have the same type.
检查这两个参数的类型是否相同
So we'll say,
所以我们要问
is the type of the first argument the same as the type of the second argument?
第一个参数的类型和第二个的类型一样吗？
And if they're not, if they're not
如果不一样
we'll go off and complain, and say, that's an error.
我们就停止运行 然后抛出错误
We don't know how to do that.
我们不知道怎么对它们进行运算
If they do have the same type,
如果它们的类型确实是相同的
we'll do exactly what we did before.
那就和之前一样了
We'll go look and filed under the type of the argument--
我们会查询在参数的类型对应的
arg 1 and arg 2 have the same type, so it doesn't matter.
参数1和参数2是同样的类型 知道一个就可以
So we'll look in the table, find the procedure.
我们到表格里去查找对应的过程
If there is a procedure there,
如果找到这样一个过程
then we'll apply it to the contents of the arg1 and the contents of arg2.
我们就将其应用在参数1和参数2的内容上
And otherwise we'll say, error.
如果是其它情况 就报错
Undefined operator.
“未定义运算符”
And so there's operate-2.
这就是operate-2过程
And that's all we have to do.
这就是我们要做的全部事情
We just built the complex number package before.
我们刚刚才写好了一个复数运算包
How do we embed that complex number package in this generic system?
那么怎么把它放进这个通用系统里面呢？
Almost the same.
方法几乎是一样的
We make a procedure called make-complex
我们构造一个叫做make-complex的过程
that takes whatever George and Martha hand to us
它把George和Martha给我们的东西
and add the type complex.
贴上complex的类型标志
And then we say, to add complex numbers, plus complex,
然后我们说 要把复数相加 这个+complex过程
we use our internal procedure, plus c,
用我们的内部过程 +c
and attach a type,
把结果加上类型
make that a complex number.
让它变成复数类型
So our original package had names plus c and minus c
那么我们的包里原来有+c和-c这两个过程
that we're using to communicate with George and Martha.
用来和George和Martha通信
And then to communicate with the outside world,
然后为了与外部通信
we have a thing called plus-complex and minus-complex.
我们还有+complex和-complex
And so on.
等等
And the only difference is that these return values that are typed
它们唯一的不同就在于：后者的返回的是带类型的值
So they can be looked at up here.
它们可以在这里被查询
And these are internal operations.
而这些是内部过程
Let's go look at that slide again.
我们再来看那个幻灯片
There's one more thing we do.
我们还有一件事要做
After defining plus-complex,
在定义了+complex之后
we put under the type complex and the symbol add,
我们在complex类型和add符号对应的格子中
that procedure plus complex.
填上过程+complex
And then similarly for subtracting complex numbers,
对于-complex也类似
and multiplying them, and dividing them.
*complex和/complex亦如此
OK, how do we install ordinary numbers?
那我们怎么安装寻常算术呢？
Exactly the same way.
方法还是一样的
Come off and say, well we'll make a thing called make-number
我们会写一个叫做make-number的过程
Make-number takes a number and attaches a type,
make-number接收一个数 然后给它加上类型
which is the symbol number.
也就是符号number
We build a procedure called plus-number,
我们构造一个过程叫做+number
which is simply, add the two things using the ordinary addition,
用Lisp自带的加法把两个数加起来
because in this case we're talking about ordinary numbers,
因为我们现在讨论的是寻常算术
and attach a type to it and make that a number.
给它加上类型 让它变成number类型
And then we put into the table under the symbol number
然后我们把+number过程放到
and the operation add, this procedure plus-number,
表格里number和add对应的的格子中
and then the same thing for subtracting, and multiplying, and dividing.
再用相同的方法把减法 乘法 除法也放进去
Let's look at an example, just to make it clear.
我们举一个例子 就看得清楚一点
Suppose, for instance,
假设 比如说
I'm going to perform the operation.
我要执行这个运算
So I sit up here and I'm going to perform the operation,
好 现在我要执行一个运算
which looks like multiplying two complex numbers.
比如说我把两个复数乘起来
So I would multiply, say, 3 plus 4i and 2 plus 6i.
把3+4i和2+6i乘起来
And that's something that I might want to take hand that to mul.
这就是我调用mul过程要传入的参数
I'll write mul as my generic operator here.
这里就代表通用运算符mul
How's that going to work?
那么它怎么工作呢
Well 3 plus 4i, say, sits in the system at this level
我们讲3+4i 在整个系统里
as something that looks like this.
处于这样的一个位置
Let's say it was one of George's.
假设它是George那种方法表示的
So it would have a 3 and a 4.
所以它的内部有一个3和一个4
And attached to that would be George's type,
这上面还贴着George的类型标志
which says rectangular, it came from George.
是他构造的rectangular类型
And attached to that--
又附加在那上面的
and this itself would be the data view from the next level up
从更上一层的视角来看这一段数据
which it is--
它又是一个
so that itself would be a type-data object
这整个又是一个带类型的数据
which would say complex.
它的类型是complex
So that's what this object would look like
那么这就是这个对象
up here at the very highest level,
在最高层视角中的样子
where the really super-generic operations are looking at it.
那些通用运算符看到的对象 就是这样的
Now what happens, mul eventually's going to come along
现在 mul过程会过来问
and say, oh,what's it's type?
它的类型是什么？
It's type is complex.
它的类型是complex
Go through to operate-2 and say,
然后运行到operate-2 然后说
oh, what I want to do is apply what's in the table,
啊 我想要把表格里的过程
which is going to be the procedure star complex,
也就是*complex这个过程
on this thing with the type stripped off.
应用到 将其类型剥离之后的结果上去
So it's going to strip off the type,
所以它会把类型剥下来
take that much, and send that down into the complex world.
把剩下的东西传递给复数的世界
The complex world looks at its operations and says,
复数的世界看了看它有的运算操作 然后说
oh, I have to apply star c.
“我得调用*c这个过程”
Star c might say,
然后*c过程说
at some point I want to look at the magnitude of this object that it's in, that it's got.
我想知道这个东西的模值是多少
And they'll say, oh, it's
然后它们会说 啊
rectangular, it's one of George's.
它是直角坐标表示的 是George的东西
So it'll then strip off the next version of type,
所以它们又剥掉了一个类型
and hand that down to George to take the magnitude of.
然后把内容交给George 让他提取出它的模值
So you see what's going on
那么我们看到
is that there are these chains of types.
这其中有一条由类型构成的链条
And the length of the chain is sort of the number of levels
这个链条的长度就是你要
that you're going to be going up in this table.
在这个表格里上升的层数
And what a type tells you,
类型的作用则是
every time you have a vertical barrier in this table,
每当我们在表格中遇到一道垂直屏障时
where there's some ambiguity about where you should go down to the next level,
你不知道该如何抉择时
the type is telling you where to go.
类型就会给你指路
And then everybody at the bottom,
然后最底层的过程
as they construct data and filter it up,
它们构造数据结构 对数据进行筛选之后
they stick their type back on.
再把类型贴回去
So that's the general structure of the system.
这就是整个系统的总体结构
OK.
好
Now that we've got this,
明白了这个之后
let's go and make this thing even more complex.
我们再让这个系统变得更加复杂
Let's talk about adding to the system not only these kinds of numbers
我们这次不光要在系统里添加新的数域
numbers, but it's also meaningful to start talking about adding polynomials.
我们也来讨论一下怎么把多项式也加进去
Might do arithmetic on polynomials.
让它能做多项式算术
Like we could have x to the fifteenth plus 2x to the seventh plus 5.
比如我们可以计算x^15+2x^7+5
That might be some polynomial.
像这样的多项式
And if we have two such gadgets
如果有两个这样的东西
we can add them or multiply them.
我们可以把它们相加或者相乘
Let's not worry about dividing them.
先不管相除的问题
Just add them, multiply them, then we'll subtract them.
只考虑相加相乘和相减
Auhhh...What do we have to do? Well
我们需要做什么
let's think about how we might represent a polynomial.
我们先来想想怎么表示一个多项式
It's going to be some typed data object.
它也是一种带类型的数据
So let's say a polynomial to this system
这个系统里的一个多项式
might look like a thing that starts with the type polynomial.
应该是带有polynomial类型的对象
And then maybe it says the next thing is what variable its in.
接下来它可能要问这个多项式的变量是哪个
So I might say I'm a polynomial in the variable x.
比如这是一个以x为变量的多项式
And then it'll have some information about what the terms are.
然后 多项式内还有各项的信息
And there're just tons of ways to do this,
有很多种方法来实现
but one way is to say we're going to have a thing called a term-list.
我们采用的方法是构造一个“项表”
And a term-list--
所谓的“项表”
well, in our case we'll use something that looks like this.
本例中 我们用的是类似这样的东西
We'll make it a bunch of pairs which have an order in a coefficient
我们把它写成一系列 按次数排列的序对
So this polynomial would be represented by this term-list.
那么这个项表就能表示这个多项式了
And what that means is that
它的意义是
this polynomial starts off with a term of order 15 and coefficient 1.
这个多项式第一项的次数是15 系数是1
And the next thing in it is a term of order 7 and coefficient 2,
然后下一项的次数是7 系数是2
a term of order 0, which is constant in coefficient 5
再下一项是一个常数 它次数是0 系数是5
And there are lots and lots of ways,
实际上有很多很多种方法
and lots and lots of trade-offs
也有很多很多的取舍
when you really think about making algebraic manipulation packages
在你认真思考如何实现代数操作程序包时
that exactly how you should represent these things.
你该如何表示这些东西
But this is a fairly standard one.
但是我们这种是比较标准的一种
It's useful in a lot of contexts.
它适用于很多情况
OK, well how do we implement our polynomial arithmetic?
好 那么我们怎么实现我们的多项式算术呢
Let's start out.
现在开始着手做这个事情
What we'll do to make a polynomial--
构造一个多项式 首先要
we'll first have a way to make polynomials.
首先我们得找一个办法来构造多项式
We're going to make a polynomial out of variable like x and term-list.
我们可以用一个变量 比如x和一个项表来构造它们
And all that does is we'll package them together someway.
我们要用某种方法把它们包装起来
We'll put the variable together with the term list using cons
我们可以用cons把变量和项表组合起来
and then attached to that the type polynomial.
然后把这个序对加上polynomial的类型标志
OK, how do we add two polynomials?
那我们怎么处理多项式相加呢？
To add a polynomial, p1 and p2,
要相加两个多项式 p1和p2
and then just for simplicity let's say we
为了简化问题 假设我们
we will only add things in the same variable.
我们只相加变量相同的两个式子
So if they have the same variable,
那么如果它们的变量相同
and same variable here is going to be some selector we write,
是否相同交由我们编写的选择函数判断
whose details we don't care about.
我们不必在意它的细节
If the two polynomials have the same variable,
如果两个多项式的变量相同
then we'll do something.
我们就继续运算
If they don't have the same variable, we'll give an error,
如果它们的变量不相同 我们返回一个错误
polynomials not in the same variable.
“两个多项式的变量不相同”
And if they do have the same variable,
如果它们的变量确实是相同
what we'll do is we'll make a polynomial
我们就要构造一个新的多项式
whose variable is whatever that variable is,
它的变量即是原式的变量
and whose term-list is something we'll call sum-terms.
它的项表则由过程+terms产生
Plus terms will add the two term lists.
+terms过程会把两个项表加起来
So we'll add the two term lists to the polynomial.
所以我们要把两个多项式的项表合起来
That'll give us a term-list.
该过程即可返回一个项表
We'll add on, we'll say it's a polynomial in the variable with that term-list.
我们将变量和得到的项表构造成新的多项式
That's plus poly.
这就是+poly过程
And then we're going to put in our table under the type polynomial
然后我们要把这个过程放进表格中polynomial那一栏
add them using plus poly.
用+poly实现add操作
And of course we really haven't done much.
当然实际上没做多少事情
What we've really done is pushed all the work onto this thing, +terms
我们只是把所有的工作压到+terms的头上
which is supposed to add term-lists.
它会负责把项表相加起来
Let's look at that.
我们看看这个过程
Here's an overview of how we might add two term-lists.
这是+terms过程的大概结构
So L1 and L2 were going to be two term-lists.
L1和L2是两个项表
And a term-list is a bunch of pairs, coefficient in order.
所谓“项表”即是按每项次数排序的序对
And it's a big case analysis.
这里有一个大的分情况分析
And the first thing we'll check for and see if there are any terms
首先 我们要检查项表是否为空
We're going to recursively work down these term-lists
我们对项表做递归下降处理
so eventually we'll get to a place where either L1 or L2 might be empty.
最终下降到 L1或L2为空
And if either one is empty,
只要其中有一个为空
our answer will be the other one.
我们的答案就是剩下的另一个
So if L1 is empty we'll return L2,
就是说如果L1是空表 我们就返回L2
and if L2 is empty we'll return L1.
L2是空表的话就返回L1
Otherwise there are sort of three interesting cases.
除此之外还有三种情况
What we're going to do is
我们要做的是
grab the first term in each of those lists,
取表中的第一项
Right? Called t1 and t2.
记为t1和t2
And we're going to look at three cases,
我们来分析一下这三种情况
depending on whether the order of t1 is greater than the order of t2,
分别是t1的次数大于t2的
or less than t2, or the same.
小于t2的 或者等于t2的
Those are the three cases we're going to look at.
这就是我们要判断的三种情况
Let's look at this case.
先看看这一种
If the order of t1 is greater than the order of t2,
如果t1的次数比t2的次数要高
then what that means is that
就意味着
then what that means is that our answer is going to start with this term of the order of t1.
答案的第一项的次数就是t1的次数
Because it won't combine with any lower order terms.
因为高次项不会和任何低次项相加
So what we do is add the lower order terms.
那么我们只需要把低次的项加起来
We recursively add
我们递归地把
together all the terms in the rest of the term-list in L1 and L2.
把L1和L2两个项表里剩下的项相加
That's going to be the lower order terms of the answer.
作为我们的答案中低次项
And then we're going to adjoin to that the highest order term.
然后我们把它们和最高次的项连接起来
And I'm using here a whole bunch of procedures I haven't defined
这里 我用了一对还未定义的过程
like a adjoin-term, and rest-terms,
比如adjoin-term、rest-terms
and selectors that get order.
还有获取次数的选择函数
But you can imagine what those are.
但是你可以想象它们是什么样子的
Right? So if the first term-list has a higher order than the second
那么如果第一个项表的次数比第二个要高
we recursively add all the lower terms
我们就递归地把所有的低次的项相加
and then stick on that last term.
再和最高次项连接起来
The other case, the same way.
其它情况也是一样的
If the first term has a smaller order,
如果第一个多项式次数比较低
well then we add we add the first term-list and the rest of the terms in the second one
我们就把整个第一个多项式和第二个多项式低次的项相加
and adjoin on this highest order term.
然后把结果再和最高次项连起来
So so far nothing's much happened,
到现在也没多少复杂的事情
we've just sort of pushed this thing off into adding lower order terms.
把问题变成 让低次数的项相加
The last case where you actually get to a coefficients
还有最后一种情况是 两个多项式的次数一样
that you have to add, this will be the case where the orders are equal.
你必须要把它们的系数加起来 因为它们是同类项
What we do is, well again recursively add the lower order terms.
我们的应对方法仍然是 递归地把低次项相加
But now we have to really combine something.
但现在我们需要合并一些项了
What we do is we make a term
我们构造一个项
whose order is the order of the term we're looking at.
其次数为我们正在处理的那一项的次数
By now t1 and t2 have the same order.
因为现在t1和t2的次数是相同的
That's its order.
确定好次数了
And its coefficient is gotten by adding the coefficient of t1 and the coefficient of t2.
而它的系数是t1和t2系数之和
There's... This is a big recursive working down of terms,
这是一个庞大的递归过程
but really there's only one interesting symbol in this procedure,
但其中只有一个符号值得玩味
only one interesting idea.
它蕴含了重要的思想
The interesting idea is this add.
那就是这个ADD过程
And the reason that's interesting is because
说它有趣是因为
something completely wonderful just happened.
有一件好事发生
We reduced adding polynomials,
我们没有把多项式加法
not to sort of plus, but to the generic add.
归约为某种加法 而是归约为通用运算符ADD
In other words, by implementing it that way,
换句话说 用这种方法实现它之后
not only do we have our system
我们的系统就不光有
where we can have rational numbers, or complex numbers, or ordinary numbers,
有理数、复数还有寻常算术
we've just added on polynomials.
我们同时也让它支持多项式运算了
But the coefficients of the polynomials
而多项式的系数可以是
can be anything that the system can add.
这个系统能够相加的任何东西
So these could be polynomials whose coefficient
也就是说多项式的系数
are rational numbers or complex numbers,
有理数或者复数
which in turn could be either rectangular, or polar,
复数同时可支持直角坐标形式和极坐标形式
or ordinary numbers.
系数还可以是寻常的数字
Rignt? So what I mean precisely is
我想说的是
our system right now automatically
我们的系统现在可以自动地
can handle things like adding together polynomials that have this form
处理像这样的式子
2/3 of x squared plus 5/17 x plus 11/4.
比如2/3x^2+5/17x+11/4这样的式子
Or automatically handle polynomials that look like
也可以自动处理像是
3 plus 2i times x to the fifth plus 4 plus 7i, or something.
(3+2i)x^5+(4+7i)这样的式子
Right? You can automatically handle those things.
系统可以自动处理这些运算
Why is that?
为什么呢？
That's merely because, or profoundly because
仅仅是因为 或者说深层次的原因是
we reduced adding polynomials to adding their coefficients.
我们把多项式相加归约成了把它们的系数相加
And adding coefficients was done by the generic add operator
而系数的相加是由通用运算符ADD完成的
which said, I don't care what your types are
它说：“我不管你的数据类型是什么”
as long as I know how to add you.
“只要我能够处理就行”
So automatically for free we get the ability to handle that.
于是我们就“免费”获得了处理这些东西的功能
What's even better than that,
更神奇的是
one of the things we did
我们曾把
we put into the table that the way you add polynomials
我们放入表格中 用于处理多项式加法
is using plus poly.
是用的+poly过程
That means that polynomials themselves are things that can be added.
这就意味着ADD过程也可以处理多项式了
So for instance let me write one here.
我举个例子
Here is... Here's a polynomial.
这是一个多项式
So this gadget here I'm writing up,
我正在写的这个东西
this is a polynomial in y
它是一个以y作为变量的多项式
whose coefficients are polynomials in x.
每项的系数是以x作为变量的多项式
So you see, simply by saying,
你将看到
polynomials are themselves things that can be added,
由于 “ADD过程能够处理多项式”
we can go off and say, well not only can we deal with rationals,
我们可以说 我们的系统现在不光能运算有理数
or complex, or ordinary numbers,
复数和一般数字
but we can deal with polynomials
我们还可以处理多项式
whose coefficients are rationals, or complex, or ordinary numbers,
多项式的系数可以是有理数、复数、一般数字
or polynomials
甚至是多项式
whose coefficients are rationals,
作为系数的多项式 其系数还可以是有理数
or complex, rectangular, polar, or ordinary numbers,
复数（直角或极坐标形式）或一般数字
or ordinary numbers, or polynomials whose coefficients are rationals,
甚至还可以是系数为有理数的多项式
complex, or ordinary numbers.
系数为复数、一般数字的多项式
And so on, and so on, and so on.
以此类推
So this is sort of an infinite
我们构造出了一座无限延伸的
or maybe a recursive tower of types that we've built up.
或者说是递归的类型高塔
And it's all exactly from that one little symbol, A-D-D.
这一切都来源于那个小小的符号：A-D-D
Writing "add" instead of "plus" in the polynomial thing.
来源于在多项式程序里 用“ADD”来代替“+”
Slightly different way to think about it
换一种方式来理解它就是
is that polynomials are a constructor for types.
多项式也是一种类型的构造函数
Namely you give it a type, like integer,
也就是说你传递给它一个类型 比如整型
and it returns for you polynomials in x whose coefficients are integers.
然后它就返回一个以整数作为系数的多项式
And the important thing about
过程中很重要的一点是
is that is that the operations on polynomials
就是多项式上的运算
reduce to the operations on the coefficients.
归约成了关于系数的运算
And there are a lot of things like that.
很多地方都与这里类似
So for example, let's go back and rational numbers.
比如 我们再回头看看有理数
We thought about rational numbers as an integer over an integer
我们之前把有理数看做 一个整数在另一个上面
but there's the general notion of a rational object.
但这并不是关于有理式的一般性记号
Like we might think about 3x plus 7 over x squared plus 1.
比如我们也可以把3x+7放在上面 x^2+1放在下面
That's general rational object whose numerator and denominator are polynomials.
这是一个分子分母都是多项式的广义有理式
And to add two of them we use the same formula,
有理式相加 和有理数相加一样
numerator times denominator plus denominator times numerator
分子乘分母 加 分母乘分子 结果作为分子
over product of denominators.
两个分母相乘 结果作为分母
How could we install that in our system?
怎么把它安装到我们的系统中呢？
Well here's our original rational number arithmetic package.
这是我们原来的有理数算术程序包
And all we have to do in order to make the entire system
为了让这个系统能够
continue working with general rational objects,
支持广义有理式的运算
is replace these particular pluses and stars by the generic operator.
我们把特定的加法和乘法过程 都改成通用运算符
So if we simply change that procedure to this one,
所以如果我们把原来那个过程变成这个过程
here we've changed plus and star to add a mul,
把+和*换成ADD和MUL
those are absolutely the only change,
这些是唯一的改动
then suddenly
然后霎时间
our entire system can start talking about objects that look like this.
我们的整个系统 就知道怎么运算这样的东西了
So for example, here is a rational object
比如说 这里的这个有理式
whose numerator is a polynomial in x whose coefficients are rational numbers.
它的分子是一个系数是有理数的、关于x的多项式
Or here is a rational object
而这个有理式
whose numerator is polynomials in x
它的分子是关于x的多项式
whose coefficients are rational objects
多项式的系数又是有理式
constructed out of complex numbers.
有理式又由复数组成
And then there are a lot of other things like that.
或者别的像这样的东西
See, whenever you have a thing where the operations reduce to operations on the pieces,
看 只要能够归约成针对各部分的运算
another example would be
另一个例子是
two by two matrices.
2*2的矩阵
I have the idea, there might be a matrix here
假如有这样一个矩阵形式的东西
of general things that I don't care about.
不管它里面是什么
But if I add two of them,
但是如果我对两个这种东西调用ADD
the answer over here is gotten by
答案就是
adding this one and that one,however they like to add.
把这个和这个相加 而矩阵是怎么相加的
So I can implement that the same way.
那么我可以用同样的方法实现
And if I do that,
如果我这么做了
then again suddenly my system can start handling things like this.
整个系统就马上可以处理像这样的东西了
So here's a matrix whose elements happen to be--
比如说一个矩阵 它的元素都是
we'll say this element here is a rational object
它的元素是一个有理式
whose numerator and denominators are polynomials.
这个有理式的分子分母都是多项式
Right? And all that comes for free.
我们自然而然地获得了这些功能
Right? What's really going on here?
整个过程中发生了什么？
What's really going on is
真正发生的是
getting rid of who's sitting there poking his nose into who everybody's business is.
我们摆脱了凡事都想插一手的经理
We built a system that has decentralized control.
我们构造了一个“控制去中心化”的系统
So when you come into and no one's poking around saying,
你进入这个系统的时候 不会有人一边闲逛一边说
gee, are you in the official list of people who can be added?
我看看官方列表中ADD是否能够处理你
Rather you say, well go off and add yourself how your parts like to be added.
你直接就可以用正确的方法 把你和别的东西加起来
And the result of that is you can get this very, very, very
这么做的好处就是 就连这种非常非常
complex hierarchy where a lot of things just get done and
复杂的分层对象也可以被分解后
rooted to the right place automatically.
自动放到正确的地方去处理
Let's stop for questions.
有什么问题吗？
AUDIENCE: You say you get this for free.
学生：你说你“免费”获得了这些功能
Um..... One thing that strikes me is that now you've lost
但是我在意的是你现在丢掉了
kind of the cleanness of the break between what's on top and what's underneath.
某种上下层之间的清楚界限
In other words, now you're defining some of the
或者说 现在你是在用
lower-level procedures in terms of things above their own line.
上层的东西来定义下层的过程
Isn't that dangerous?
这不是很危险吗？
Or, if nothing more, a little less structured?
或者说 结构会变得混乱？
PROFESSOR: No, I--
教授：不 我--
the question is whether that's less structured.
你问它的结构是否混乱
Depends on what you mean by structure.
这得要看你说的“结构”是指什么
All this is doing is recursion.
整个过程里我们都在做递归
See, it's saying that the way you add these guys is to use that.
看 就是说要把这些东西相加就要用到这个过程
And that's not less structured, it's just a recursive structure.
它是一种递归结构 并不混乱
So I don't think it's particularly any less clean.
所以我不认为它不清楚
AUDIENCE: Now when you want to change the multiplier or the add operator
学生：那么当你修改乘法或加法运算时
suddenly you've got tremendous consequences
可能会导致
underneath that you're not even sure the extent of.
无法预测的灾难性后果
PROFESSOR: That's right, but it depends what you mean.
教授：你说得对 但是那要看你的意思是什么
See, this goes both ways.
从两个角度来讨论
Um....What would be a good example?
举个什么例子好呢？
I ignored greatest common divisor, for instance.
比如说 之前我忽略了GCD运算
I ignored that problem just to keep the example simple.
我们忽略了它 是为了简化我们的例子
But if I suddenly decided that plus rat here
但是如果突然我觉得 这里的+rat
should do a GCD computation and install that,
应该把结果约分 然后把这个功能安装到程序里
then that immediately becomes available to all of these, to that guy, and that guy,
那么这个功能一旦安装 就立刻可以被所有过程调用
and that guy, and all the way down.
被这个或者那个 所有的这些
So it depends what you mean by the coherence of your system.
这取决于你系统的相干性（耦合度）
It's certainly true that you might want to have a special
确实你可能想设计一个
different one that didn't filter down through the coefficients
不这样递归下降的程序
but the nice thing about this particular example is that mostly you do.
但是我举这个例子的好处 就在于我们通常都是这么做的
AUDIENCE: Isn't that the problem, I think, that you're
学生：是不是有一个问题 我想
getting to tied in with the fact that the structuring, the
就是你会被这个结构捆绑起来
recursiveness of that structuring there is actually
这个递归的结构是实际上被执行了的
in execution as opposed to just definition of the actual
而不是仅仅是为了定义类型的需要
types themselves?
被这个事实所束缚
PROFESSOR: I think I understand the question.
教授：我大概明白你的意思
The point is that these types evolve
你是想说在这个系统投入运行之后
and get more and more complex as the thing's actually running.
这些类型还会变得越来越复杂
Is that what--
你是不是想……
AUDIENCE: Yap.
学生：对
As it's running.
在它投入运行之后
AUDIENCE: As opposed to the basic definitions.
学生：而不是作为基本的定义
PROFESSOR: Right. There's...
教授：对
The type structure is sort of recursive.
我们的类型结构可以说就是递归的
It's not that you can make this finite list of the
它并不是一个 可以在系统投入运行之前
actual things they might look like before the system runs.
就能把要用到的东西全部包括的列表
It's something that evolves.
它是一个不断演进的东西
So if you want to specify that system,
所以如果你想要定制这个系统
you have to do in some other way than by this finite list.
你就不能通过有限的表
You have to do it by a recursive structure.
你需要用一个递归结构实现它
AUDIENCE: Because the basic structure of the types is pretty clean and simple.
学生：因为类型的基本结构是相当简单而明了的
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：对
Yes?
嗯？
AUDIENCE: I have a question.
学生：我有一个问题
I understand once you have your data structure set up,
我明白一旦你的数据结构被设计好之后
how it pulls off complex and passes that down,
它是怎么把complex标志拿掉 把它传递给下层
and then pulls off rect, passes that down.
然后把rect类型拿掉 再传递给下层
But if you're just a user and you don't know anything about rect or polar or whatever,
但是如果你只是一个用户 并不知道什么rect或者polar类型
how do you initially set up that data structure
你怎么知道如何去设置这个数据结构
so that everything goes to the right spot?
让所有东西正常运转呢
If I just have the equation over there on the left
如果我只知道左边的这个算式
And I just want to add, multiply complex numbers--
我只是想把复数加起来或者乘起来
PROFESSOR: Well that's the wonderful thing.
教授：这就是它神奇的地方
If you're just a user you say "mul."
如果你是一个用户 直接调用mul就可以了
AUDIENCE: And it figures out that I mean complex numbers?
学生：然后它就能明白我要计算的是复数？
Or how do I tell it that I want--
或者我怎么告诉它我想——
PROFESSOR: Well you're going to have in your hands complex numbers.
教授：只要你给它的是复数它就能明白
See what you would have at some level, as a real user,
作为这个系统的用户
is a constructor for complex numbers.
你能使用的是复数的构造函数
AUDIENCE: So then I have to make complex numbers?
学生：那么我需要自己构造复数了？
PROFESSOR: So you have to make them.
教授：那么你需要自己构造它们
What you would probably have as a user is some little thing in the reader loop,
作为用户 你可能只能够操作命令行
which would give you some plausible way
它会给你提供一些合理的方法
to type in a complex number,
来输入复数
in however whatever format you like.
让你用你喜欢的格式输入
Or it might be that you're never typing them in.
也可能你根本就不用输入它们
Someone's just handing you a complex number.
只是别人给你一个复数让你计算
AUDIENCE: OK, so if I had a complex number that had a polynomial in it,
学生：好 那么如果我有一个含有多项式的复数
I'd have to make my polynomial and then make my complex number.
我就要先构造这个多项式 然后再构造我的复数
PROFESSOR: Right if you wanted it constructed from scratch.
教授：如果你是从零开始构造它的话 是这样的
At some point you construct them from scratch.
可以说你是在从零开始构造
But what you don't have to know of that
而你只要有了要计算的东西
is when you have the object you can just say "mul." And it'll multiply.
可以直接调用mul运算 然后它们就会被乘起来
Yeah?
说吧
AUDIENCE: I think the question that was being posed here is,
学生：我想提一个问题 就是……
say if I want to change my presentation of complexes,
比如说我想修改我的复数表示方法
or some operation of complex,
或者复数的某些运算
how much real code I will have to gets around with,
为了修改一个特定的运算
or change to change it in one specific operation?
我得考虑多少代码？
PROFESSOR: [UNINTELLIGIBLE] what you have to change.
教授：得看你想要修改什么
And the point is that you only have to change
重点在于你只需要改
what you're changing.
你想改的那一部分
See if Martha decides that she would rather--
想象一下如果Martha决定她
let's see something silly--
举个不太好的例子
like change the order in the pair.
比如把序对中两个数的顺序调换
Like angle and magnitude in the other order,
把模和辐角的顺序反过来
she just makes that change locally.
她只做了局部的修改
And the whole thing will propagate through the system in the right way.
那么这个改动会准确无误地扩散到整个系统里
Or if suddenly you said, gee, I have another representation for rationals.
或者突然你说 我有另一种方法来表示有理数
And I'm going to stick it here, by filing those operations in the table.
我就得不断地在表格中添加运算
Then suddenly all of these polynomials whose coefficients
那么突然之间所有的多项式
are coefficients of coefficients, or whatever,
它们的系数和系数的系数 或者什么东西
also can automatically have available that representation.
都自动支持用这种表示方法来表示了
That's the power of this particular one.
这就是我们这种设计的威力
AUDIENCE: I'm not sure if I can even pose an intelligent sounding question.
学生：我提的这个问题可能听起来比较蠢
But somehow this whole thing went really nicely
整个这个系统看起来
to this beautiful finish where all the things seemed to fall into place.
非常完美 所有的东西都各就各位
And sort of seemed a little contrived.
完美得有点出乎意料
That's all for the sake, I'm sure, of teaching.
我相信 这都是为了教学方便
I doubt that the guys who first did this--
我怀疑的是首先发明了这种做法的人
and I could be wrong--
我可能说得不对
figured it all out so that when they just all put it all together,
难道一下子就搞清楚了所有这些东西一起
you could all of the sudden, blam, do any kind of arithmetic on any kind of object.
只要把这些放在一起 你就突然可以对各种对象做各种运算
It seems like maybe they had to play with it for a while
我觉得他们应该研究了很长时间
and had to bash it and rework it.
不断地推倒重来
And it seems like that's the kind of problem we're really
然后我觉得 当我们设计一个非常复杂的系统
faced with we start trying to design a really complex system
我们也要面对这样的问题
is having lots of different kinds of parts and not even knowing
就是有太多各种各样的部件 我们甚至不知道
what kinds of operations we're going to want to do on those parts.
我们甚至不知道要对这些部件做什么样的操作
How to organize the operations in this nice way
在这种时候我怎么用这种良好的方法组织操作
so that no matter what you do, when you start putting them together
才能获得这种 不管怎样只要把它们放在一起
everything starts falling out for free.
所有事情就正常运转 这样的效果呢
PROFESSOR: OK, well that's certainly a very intelligent question... Um
教授：很好 这确实是一个非常聪明的问题
Um....One part is this is a very good methodology
要说的一点是我们这种方法论
that people have discovered a lot coming from symbolic algebra.
受到了符号代数的很多启发
Because there are a lot of complications.
符号代数相当繁复
To allow you to implement these things before you decide
允许你在决定各种运算是什么样子之前
what you want all the operations to be, and all of that.
来实现这个系统
So in some sense it's an answer that people have discovered by wading through this stuff.
所以从某种意义上讲 这是人们在这方面长期探索之后得出的答案
In another sense, it is a very contrived example.
从另一个角度来说 这确实是精心设计的例子
AUDIENCE: It seems like to be able to do this you do have to
学生：看上去想要设计出这样的系统
wade through it for a certain amount of time before you can become good at it.
一开始先要研究一段时间然后才能变熟练
PROFESSOR: Let me show you how terribly contrived this is.
教授：我给你看看这个东西是多么的勉强
So you can write all these wonderful things.
你现在可以写下所有的这些程序
But the system that I wrote here,
但是我写在这里的这个系统
and if we had another half an hour to give this lecture
如果允许我拖堂半小时的话
I would have given this part of it,
我会给大家讲
which says, notice that it breaks down
如果我让它做一个错误操作
if I tell it to do something as foolish as add 3 plus 7/2.
比如一个愚蠢的命令 用3加上7/2 它就会崩溃
Because what will happen is you'll get to operate-2,
因为程序首先会调用operate-2这个过程
and operate-2 will say, oh this is type number,
然后operate-2会说 这个是数字类型
and that's type rational.
那个是有理数类型
I don't know how to add them.
我不知道怎么把它们加起来
So you'd like the system at least to be able to say something like,
那么你想让这个系统至少能够
gee,before you do that
比如说 在做这个操作之前
change that to 3/1.
把3提升为3/1
Turn it into a rational number, hand that to the rational package.
把它变成一个有理数 然后交给有理数程序包来处理
That's the thing I didn't talk about in this lecture.
课堂上我们来不及讲这个问题了
It's a little bit in the book,which talks about the problem
书里面讨论了这个问题
of what's called coercion.
叫做“类型转换”
Where you wanted--
你想要的是
see, having so carefully set up all of these types as distinct objects
看 我们小心翼翼地把对象按类型分好类
a lot of times you want to also put in knowledge
但是有时你也想让它
about how to view an ordinary number as a kind of rational.
知道怎么把一个普通的数字当成有理数
Or view an ordinary number as a kind of complex.
或者把普通的数字当成复数
That's where the complexity in the system really starts happening
到那个时候系统就开始变得复杂了
where you talk about, see where do I put that knowledge?
就是你去思考 我应该把这些知识放在哪里的时候
Is it rational to know that ordinary numbers might be pieces of cons of them?
是应该让有理数知道它们是由普通的数字构成的吗？
Or they're terrible, terrible examples, like
或者我们举一个更加糟糕的例子
if I might want to add a complex number to a rational number.
比如说我想要把一个复数加到有理数上去
Bad example.
这个不好
5/7.
5/7
Then somebody's got to know that
然后整个系统里必须有人知道
I have to convert these to another type,
他需要把这个东西变成另一种类型
which is complex numbers whose parts might be rationals.
要把它变成一部分是有理数的复数
And who worries about that?
那么谁应该去操心这个事情呢
Does complex worry about that?
是complex程序包吗？
Does rational worry about that?
是rational程序包吗？
Does plus worry about that?
还是plus过程要考虑这个问题？
That's where the real complexity comes in.
这就是体现复杂性的地方
And that's where it's pretty well sorted out.
也是这个问题的特别之处
And a lot of, in fact, all of this message passing stuff
同时很多的 实际上是所有的这样的“消息传递”的想法
was motivated by problems like this.
都是被这样的问题启发的
And when you really push it, people are--
当你真正深入进去
somehow the algebraic manipulation problem seems to be so complex
人们发现 代数操作的问题是如此复杂
that the people who are always at the edge of it are exactly in
而那些一直围绕它们工作的人们 确实就处在
the state you said.
你说的那种状态
They're wading through this thing, mucking around,
他们在这些问题里艰难跋涉 时不时陷进泥里
seeing what they use, trying to distill stuff.
寻找好用的工具 并试着提炼一种通用方法
AUDIENCE: I just want to come back to this issue of complexity once more.
学生：我想再一次回到这个复杂度的问题上来
Um... It certainly seems to be true that you have a great deal of
在修改底层过程的时候 这个系统
flexibility in altering the lower level kinds of things.
毫无疑问 体现了非常大的灵活性
But it is true that you are, in a sense,
但是确实 在某种意义上讲
freezing higher level operations.
冻结了高层运算
Or at least if you change them you don't know where all of
或者至少如果你修改它们 你不知道
the changes are going to show up, or how they are.
改动会体现在哪里 会怎么体现出来
PROFESSOR: OK, that's an extremely good question.
教授：这个问题真是不能再好了
What I have to do is,
我要做的事情就是
if I decide there's a new general operation
如果我决定添加一个通用操作
called equality test,
比如equality-test
then all of these people have to decide
那么系统中的其它人就要查表格
whether or not they would like to have an equality test by looking in the table.
来看他们需不需要支持equality-test
There're ways to decentralize it even more.
我们可以让它变得更加去中心化
That's what I sort of hinted at last time, where I said
这就是之前我提示了很多次的事情
you could not only have this type as a symbol,
你不但可以通过给对象添加符号标签来体现类型
but you actually might store in each object the operations that it knows of that.
而是把每一类对象接受的运算也保存在里面
So you might have things like greatest common divisor,
那么你可以添加一个 比如说最大公约数过程
which is a thing here which is defined only for integers,
它只能计算整数
and not in general for rational numbers.
而不是对所有有理数都通用
So it might be a very, very fragmented system.
所以这个系统可能是非常非常碎片化的
And then depending on where you want your flexibility,
取决于你想让哪一部分比较灵活
You...there's a whole spectrum of places that you  can build that in.
有一系列的地方让你把这个东西放进去
But you're pointing at the place where this starts being weak,
但是你也指出了这种设计的弱点
that there has to be some agreement on top here about these general operations.
就是必须在顶层 对于这些通用运算符有一些约定
Or at least people have to think about them.
或者至少人们要考虑这件事情
Or you might decide, you might have a table that's very sparse
或者你可以决定 把这个表格设计得非常稀疏
that only has a few things in it.
里面只放很少的一点东西
But there are lot of ways to play that game.
这个游戏有很多种玩法
OK, thank you.
谢谢大家
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP